Guide to the George Breitman Papers TAM.169
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series IV. Writings, Lectures, and Interviews, 1919-1989; 4.5 Linear Feet in 26 containers
  - Subseries H: Wald, Alan, 1974-1986
    - Wald, Alan Morrow, Felix, undated (Box 58, Folder 4)
    - Wald, Alan "Memories of the Dewey Commission: forty years later", 1977 (Box 58, Folder 5)
    - Wald, Alan "Sculptor on the left: Duncan Ferguson & the search for wholeness", circa 1981 (Box 58, Folder 6)
    - Wald, Alan: Wolfe, Bernard - obituary, 1985 (Box 58, Folder 7)
  - Subseries I: Sinclair, Louis, 1968-1986
    Louis Sinclair (1909-1990) was an author of several bibliographical works on Leon Trotsky and the Fourth International.
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1968 (Box 59, Folder 1)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1969 (Box 59, Folder 2)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1970 (Box 59, Folder 3)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1971 (Box 59, Folder 4)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1972 (Box 59, Folder 5)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1973 (Box 59, Folder 6)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 59, Folder 7)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1977 (Box 59, Folder 8)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1978 (Box 59, Folder 9)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1979 (Box 60, Folder 1)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1980 (Box 60, Folder 2)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1981 (Box 60, Folder 3)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1982 (Box 60, Folder 4)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 60, Folder 5)
    - Sinclair, Louis correspondence, 1986 (Box 60, Folder 6)
  - Subseries J: General Correspondence, 1972-1983
    - Archer, John correspondence, 1976-1980 (Box 61, Folder 1)
    - Broue, Pierre correspondence, 1972 (Box 61, Folder 2)
    - Broue, Pierre correspondence, Dec 1975-Dec 1977 (Box 61, Folder 3)
    - Broue, Pierre correspondence, 1978 (Box 61, Folder 4)
    - Broue, Pierre correspondence, 1979 (Box 61, Folder 5)
    - Broue, Pierre correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Dreyfus, Michel correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 61, Folder 7)
    - Heijenoot, Jean van correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 61, Folder 8)
    - Kofsky, Frank correspondence, 1966-1970 (Box 61, Folder 9)
    - London, Nat correspondence, 1975-1980 (Box 61, Folder 10)
    - Marazzi, Antonella and Roberto correspondence, 1978 (Box 61, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 61, Folder 12)
    - Orveillon, Jean-Claude correspondence, 1976-1977 (Box 61, Folder 13)
    - Shriver, George correspondence, 1976-1980 (Box 61, Folder 14)
  - Subseries K: Writings by Others, 1974-1985
    - Stapleton on The Today Show, 1957; cuid42805 (Box 69, Audiocassette 169_0004)
      Preservation Note: Side 1 has poor audio, side 2 is blank.
    - "Lecture on Daumier" by George Weissmann, 1958; cuid42803 (Box 69, Audiocassette 169_0002)
      Preservation Note: Muddy sound.
    - "Cuba As I Saw It" by Farrell Dobbs, April 29, 1960; cuid42804 (Box 69, Audiocassette 169_0003)
    - "The Theory of the Permanent Revolution: The Development of the Theory in Russia" by Joseph Hansen, 1961; cuid42806 (Box 69, Audiocassette 169_0005)
    - "The Theory of the Permanent Revolution: The Application of the Theory to Cuba" by Joseph Hansen, 1961; cuid42807 (Box 69, Audiocassette 169_0006)
    - Wright, John G. (Usick Vandler), 1974-1977 (Box 61A, Folder 12)
    - London, Nathaniel: "The National Question and the Left Opposition in France, 1928-30: the debate on Alsace and Indochina", 1977 (Box 61A, Folder 10)
    - London, Nathaniel: "Trotsky, Trotskyism and the National Question", 1978 (Box 61A, Folder 11)
    - "Marxism in Our Time" by Jack Barnes, L.A. Militant Forum, February 16, 1980; cuid42845 (Box 70, Audiocassette 169_0059)
      Preservation Note: This tape's cartridge was replaced.
    - Bob Lathers Interview, September 16, 1981; cuid42888 (Box 71, Audiocassette 169_0138)
    - V. R. Dunne, January 18, 1982; cuid42891 (Box 71, Audiocassette 169_0141)
      Preservation Note: The tape was reshelled.
    - John Enestvedt, February 28, 1982; cuid42887 (Box 71, Audiocassette 169_0137)
      Preservation Note: The signal is distorted.
    - Feeley, Dianne: "What Cannon learned in the early Communist Party", November 1982 (Box 61A, Folder 6)
    - "Marx and Engels as Revolutionary Fighters and Thinkers" by Betsey Stone, Los Angeles, November 13, 1982; cuid42850 (Box 70, Audiocassette 169_0066)
    - "Revolutionary Cuba Today" by Michael Pendas, Los Angeles, November 13, 1982; cuid42848
      - Part one, cuid42848A (Box 70, Audiocassette 169_0062)
      - Part two, cuid42848B (Box 70, Audiocassette 169_0063)
    - Le Blanc, Paul: "Permanent revolution in Nicaragua", September 1983 (Box 61A, Folder 8)
    - Camejo, Peter: "Against centrism - the evolution of the Socialist Workers Party, 1978-1983" (Box 61A, Folder 4)
    - Workers and Farmers Government by Evelyn Sells, June 24, 1984; cuid42895 (Box 71, Audiocassette 169_0145)
    - Alexander, Robert: The Socialist Workers Party purge of the early 1980s and its aftermath, 1984 (Box 61A, Folder 1)
    - Le Blanc, Paul: "Revolutionary Marxism against Stalinism: Trotsky on the USSR and world revolution", 1984 (Box 61A, Folder 9)
    - [Camejo, Peter]: "Fatalism vs critical consciousness, and an addendum on Pedro Camejo's Against sectarianism," by "Y", 1984 (Box 61A, Folder 5)
    - Flynn, Sean: "The Socialist Workers Party in crisis;" other articles, circa 1985 (Box 61A, Folder 7)
    - Ben Said Article, August 10, 1986; cuid42890 (Box 71, Audiocassette 169_0140)
    - Broue, Pierre: "Party opposition to Stalin (1930-1937) and the first Moscow trial", undated (Box 61A, Folder 2)
    - Broue, Pierre: "Revolution et contre revolution culturelle en Union Sovietique", undated (Box 61A, Folder 3)
    - J. Hansen, Undated; cuid42878
      - Part two, cuid42878A (Box 71, Audiocassette 169_0125)
      - Part one, cuid42878B (Box 71, Audiocassette 169_0126)
    - Lecture Compilation, Undated; cuid42857 (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 169_0078)
      Includes "World Lemt," Israel; Political Report, W.L.; Israel, W.L., Chicano; W.L., Chicano.
      Preservation Note: 4 track mono captured in two passes. The audio was digitally stretched. The recording speed was 1.875 ips and the transfer speed was 3.75 ips.
- Series V. Lists and Indexes, undated, 1981; 4 Linear Feet in 4 containers
  Series V. Lists and Indexes, contains general and special topic contents lists and indexes for the Trotskyist press, principally that of the SWP, and several lists of pseudonyms.
  - Audiotape Inventories, 1960s (Box 44, Folder 3, Box Shared Tamiment 157, Folder 23)
  - Barnes, Jack: list of writings in internal bulletins, books, pamphlets, The Militant, et al., 1967-1983, undated (Box 62, Folder 1)
  - Contents lists compiled by Louis Sinclair: Young Spartacus, The Communist, The Flag, Permanente Revolution(German), undated (Box 62, Folder 2)
  - English language [Trostkyist] bulletins of the 1930s: a list and table of contents, compiled by Louis Sinclair, undated (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - Index, 1934-1960 ( New International; Fourth International; International Socialist Review), undated (Box 62, Folder 4)
  - Internal Bulletins, contents list: CLA, WP, 1931-1936, undated (Box 62, Folder 5)
  - International Bulletins, contents list (CLO), 1931-1933, undated (Box 62, Folder 6)
  - Labor Action(San Francisco): Articles list, 1:1-16, Nov. 28, 1936-May 1, 1937, undated (Box 62, Folder 7)
  - The Militant- list of obits and death notices, 1929-1981, undated (Box 62, Folder 8)
  - The Militant- articles list, 1928-1930; index, 1931, undated (Box 62, Folder 9)
  - The Militant- index, 1932; articles lists 1933-1934, undated (Box 62, Folder 10)
  - The Militant- articles by George Lavan and James Thayer, 1947-1976, list of, undated (Box 62, Folder 11)
  - The Militant articles - GLW (George Weissman?), FL (Frank Lovell), GL (George Lavan), JTC (James Thayer), GB (George Breitman), 1946-1969, list of, undated (Box 62, Folder 12)
  - New Militant: index v. 1 and 2, Dec 15, 1934-Jun 6, 1936, undated (Box 62, Folder 13)
  - Pseudonyms (compiled by Pierre Broue), undated (Box 62, Folder 14)
  - Pseudonyms, Liste des, 1981 (Box 62, Folder 15)
  - Socialist Appeal (Chicago): articles list, v. 1-3, 1935-1937, undated (Box 62, Folder 16)
  - Socialist Appeal (New York): index 1:1-20, Aug 14-Dec 25, 1937 [by subject, country, author], undated (Box 62, Folder 17)
  - Socialist Appeal, 1938: list of articles, undated (Box 62, Folder 18)
  - Socialist Appeal: index, Jan-Jul 1939 [by author, country, subject], undated (Box 62, Folder 19)
  - Socialist Appeal, Jul-Dec 1939 - contents list, author index, undated (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - Socialist Workers Party: contents lists for Internal Bulletins, 1939-1981, undated (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - Socialist Workers Party (World War II era) - pseudonyms, undated (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - Trotsky: a chronological list of Leon Trotsky published writings, 1929-1940, Pathfinder Press, undated (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Women's Liberation: writings in the Socialist Workers Party press, undated (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - Young Spartacus: articles list, 1931-1935, undated (Box 63, Folder 6)
- Series VI. Addendum, 1940s-1980s; 5 Linear Feet in 5 containers
  Series VI. Addendum contains materials donated after the first accession to Tamiment. It contains correspondence between Dorothea and George Breitman, materials and meeting minutes from many committees of the Socialist Workers Party, Breitman's personal journals, FOIA files for both Breitmans, and National Caucus of Labor Committees materials, dating mostly from the 1970s-1980s.
  This series has not been arranged by an archivist.
  - Box 64, 1940s-1980s
    This box contains mostly correspondence between George Breitman and his wife, Dorothea, from the 1940s-1980s. The box also contains handwritten notes, a speech, a song book, and a bibliography on Leon Trotsky. The box also contains materials on the International Typographical Union, the Emergency National Campaign against US Intervention in Central America/The Caribbean, the Prometheus Research Library, and the Socialist Workers Party (SWP), which includes materials from the National Coordinators meetings, and other radical groups. There is a significant amount of materials in this box on Dorothea (Dorothy) including FOIA files and materials on her expulsion from the SWP.
  - Box 65, 1973-1981
    This box contains Michigan State Police files on George Breitman and his wife, Dorothea, and journals kept by Breitman. The box also contains a significant amount of memos, correspondence, circulars, meeting minutes, and other materials generated by committees in the Socialist Workers Party, from 1973-1981.
  - Box 66, 1970-1978
    The box contains memos, correspondence, circulars, meeting minutes, and other materials generated by committees in the Socialist Workers Party, from 1973-1978. Most of the materials are from the Rochester Labor Committee and National Caucus of Labor Committees, including internal documents, external leaflets, news bulletins, issues of New Solidarity, the newspaper of the National Caucus of Labor Committees and the U.S. Labor Party, and other materials.
  - Box 67, 1969-1981
    This box contains meeting minutes from the Administrative Committee, Elections Campaign Committee, National Committee Plenum, Organization Committee, Political Bureau, Trade Union Coordinating Committee, and the United Secretariat of the Fourth International of the Socialist Workers Party. The box also contains SWP reports and the Young Socialist Alliance materials. The box also contains a manuscript written by Breitman. The majority of the box is made up of materials from the SWP's Political committee, including minutes and some memos, dating mostly from the 1970s and 1980s.
  - Box 68, 1976
    The box is made up of materials from the Socialist Workers Party's Political committee, including minutes and some memos, dating mostly from 1976.
- Series VII. Photographs, 1916-1982; .5 Linear Feet in 1 container
  Series VII. Photographs contains photographs of the George and Dorothea Breitman, including photographs of Breitman as a youth and during World War II. Other individuals documented in the photographs are Eden Churchill, Lenin, Trotsky, and Carl Skoglund and his family.
  - Dorothea Breitman, undated (Box 68, Folder 1)
  - George Breitman, 1928, 1940s (Box 68, Folder 2)
  - Eden Churchill et al, undated (Box 68, Folder 3)
  - Communist League of America for the Fourth International, 1934 (Box 68, Folder 4)
  - Lenin from Lenin's Last Struggle by Moshe Lewin, undated (Box 68, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Friends and Comrades, undated, 1980-1982 (Box 68, Folder 6)
  - Carl Skoglund, 1916-1946 (Box 68, Folder 7)
  - Leon Trotsky, undated (Box 68, Folder 8)